A Guide to the Booth Tarkington Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #7416-b
Booth Tarkington Collection 1892-1945
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
7416-b
29 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit [ 1963 Dec 17 ] 1966 May 16
Item Listing
- Manuscripts
  - Essay, "Flowers for the Living", n. d.; AMsS, 5 p.
    [Tribute to Julian Street. ]
  - Page 244 of The Two Vanrevels, [1901]; AMs, 1 p.
  - Introduction to A World Worth While, 1922 Feb; TMs, 2 p.
    [Includes autograph corrections.]
  - Essay on Wayman Adams, 1940 Jul 9; TMsS, 4 p.
    [Includes printed advertisement for a short film entitled " Wayman Adams Painting a Portrait."]
- Letters
  - Booth Tarkington to [John Kendrick] Bangs, 1892 Apr 9; ALS, 2 p.
    [Sends thanks of cast and crew of "Katherine" for telegram which was read to the cast before the curtain; writes that it inspired the cast; believes the performance of "Katherine" was more professional and scholarly than the other production of the [Princeton College Dramatic] Association; believes audience enjoyed it; states that [J. C. B.] Pendleton will send an accounting of books sold in the lobby.]
  - Booth Tarkington to John Russell Davidson, 1901 Jan 26; ALS, 2 p.
    [Includes typed copy; recommends Charles Fisk Dalton as a man of character and ability in literary matters.]
  - Booth Tarkington to Hart, [1904 ?]; ALS, 2 p.
    [Declines invitation to dinner; plans to take his wife to a dinner given by George Harvey in honor of H[enry] James; asks for forgiveness for delaying his response; writes that he is almost as irresponsible as Oliver Herford. ]
  - Booth Tarkington to "Albert Wrightlought", 1906 Apr 26; ALS, 4 p.
    [Satirically prohibits further communication or access to box-office, yacht or club; describes grand dinner given by "Handsome Newt Tarkenheimer" for "Hon. Ed. Simmings"; gives examples of "Simmings'" restrained vocabulary because of the presence of young ladies.]
  - Booth Tarkington to F. A. Duneka, ca. 1906; ALS, 4 p.
    [States that he has sent manuscript of [
    Of His Own People
    ]; praises [Lawrence] Mazzanovitch's paintings; asks that Mac write him; comments favorably on Mark Lee Luther's latest novel; writes that he is working on a comedy drama with H. L. Wilson; requests that "
    Cord and Creese
    " and "
    The Dodge Club
    " be sent to him; hopes "
    A Castle in Spain
    The American Baron
    " will be included in the DeMiller; urges commission be given to Mazzanovitch.]
  - Booth Tarkington to Grace R. Henry, 1910 Feb 13; ALS, 3 p. w/env
    [Gives permission to perform "Monsieur Beaucaire" for charity event, waiving his share of the fee although the estate of his collaborator, [Evelyn Greenleaf] Sutherland, will collect her share; states that the manuscript can be obtained from R. Cooper McGrue of Elizabeth Marbury's firm; explains that sets are simple and the number of characters may be cut, as the play has been performed with fifty under [Richard] Mansfield and thirteen under [Crestor ?] Clark. ]
  - Booth Tarkington to [F. A.] Duneka, [1912] Oct 5; ALS, 2 p.
    [Thanks him for the pictures, which are right for light comedy; believes those by Miss Green were too serious; states that he is finishing
    The Flirt
    which will begin in the
    Saturday Evening Post
    on December 1; writes that he received "
    Mark Twain
    " from [A. B.] Paine and finds it to be exceptionally well written.]
  - Booth Tarkington to [Albert B.] Boyden, 1916 Aug 16; ALS, 3 p.
    [Writes that he has no pictures of himself, but recommends reproducing the portrait by Wayman Adams; mentions that he is "spending the summer at the Doubleday-Page bookshop in the Lord & Taylor store on Fifth Avenue."]
  - Booth Tarkington to Sylvester Baxter, 1919 Jul 24; TLS, 1 p.
    [Apologizes; states that they will do it.]
  - Booth Tarkington to Thomas L. Masson, 1920 Jul 2; TLS
    [Regrets missing the seance; writes he has been busy rewriting a play; hopes to see him at Kennebunk Beach and learn what happened.]
  - Booth Tarkington to Mr. Stearns, 1921 Jan 14; ALS, 1 p.
    [Says his association with Richard Harding Davis was infrequent although it covered 15 years; feels every meeting made him "exhilarated and optimistic."]
  - Booth Tarkington to Mr. [Schuler ?], 19[21] Sep 16; ALS, 2 p.
    [Signs N.B.T.; encloses the note suggested; requests proofs of serial; wishes to change the wording in ["Jinny's"] letter; fear it will give readers the wrong impression of "Anne."]
  - Booth Tarkington to W. Orton Tewson, 1924 Aug 18; TLS, 1 p.
    [Thanks him for note; says he will remember the [request for a submission to the
    Literary Review
    ].]
  - Booth Tarkington to W. Orton Tewson, 1924 Sep 29; TLS, 1 p.
    [Declines request to review a book because of other commitments.]
  - Booth Tarkington to Carl [Brandt], 1932 Sep 22; TLS, 1 p.
    [Expresses thanks for the "gadget"; describes meeting with a Boston detective and an individual who suspect 2 summer visitors of his burglary as well as abducting Raymond Robbins; appreciates Brandt's bringing the portrait when he comes; hopes to identify the painter's style.]
  - Booth Tarkington to J[ames] A[rthur] Tufts, 1934 Jun 1; TLS, 2 p. w/env
    [Regrets being unable to attend his class reunion at the Phillips Exeter Academy; writes that his ten year ordeal with vision problems has left him a "nervous invalid" whose "dancing days are over."]
  - Booth Tarkington to Hamilton Holt, 1935 Jun 6; TLS, 3 p.
    [Regrets being unable to receive an honorary degree from Rollins College and participating in its
    Animated Magazine
    says that a nervous disorder makes it impossible for him to be among large groups; mentions happy memories of Archie Bradshaw and Ethel Moore in Brooklyn and Holt's in-laws, Berkley Smith and family.]
  - Booth Tarkington to [ Chester W. Cleveland], 1945 Jan 26; TLS (mimeographed), 1 p.
    [Includes item from the
    Chicago Sunday Tribune
    , 1945 Jan 14; thanks him for copies of
    Magazine of Sigma Chi
    memorializing George Ade; praises the tribute to an exceptional man and suggests that it be "made into a book."]
  - Booth Tarkington to Mr. Halter, 1945 May 4; TLS, 1 p.
    [Comments on the difficulty of being objective about one's own work; states he rarely re-reads his books; finds it too painful; judges his best work to be the most recent,
    Kate Fennigate
    a year or so ago,
    Josephine
    now, something else later.]
  - Booth Tarkington to Mr. Archer, 1945 May 29; TLS, 1 p.
    [Expresses familiarity with Tolstoy's
    Kingdom of God
    hopes it encourages the idea that the Russian mind is open to world peace if we do not arm ourselves and force them to do the same; mentions a Tolstoy Society was formed by Quakers but is uncertain whether or not it still exists; encloses comments on peacetime conscription.]
  - Booth Tarkington to Brown, Aug 24; ALS, 2 p.
    [Signs N. B. Tarkington; accompanies a letter of introduction to S. Adams of the advertising staff of
    McClures
    who will know whom to contact at
    Harper's
    suggests getting a letter from Riley to
    Century
    , from Major to MacMillan Publishing Co., and from Curtis of B. M. to Dodd, Mead, Scribner's, Appleton, etc.; hopes McClures will be satisfactory.]
  - Booth Tarkington to Mary Ransdell, n. d.; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    [Invites her to Mrs. Fraser's dance; hopes many months of atonement have resulted in "absolution" and a positive reply.]
- Photographs
  - Summer home of Booth Tarkington, n. d.; Postcard
    [Signed by Booth Tarkington. ]
  - Booth Tarkington, seated with dogs, n. d.; Photo
    [Signed.] (Mounted on red border)
- Miscellaneous
  - Quotation from Alice in Wonderland signed by Booth Tarkington, QS